A Guide to the Wickham Family Papers, 1754-1977
Virginia Historical Society
General Wickham's correspondence, 1862-1888, covers any of the same subjects as do his letterbooks, with the addition of letters concerning the offer of the post of Secretary of the Navy to Wickham in the administration of James A. Garfield in 1880 and Wickham's own efforts to acquire information on his ancestors. Prominent correspondents include Cornelius Clarke Baldwin (concerning Joseph Glover Baldwin and Benjamin Watkins Leigh), Doctor Charles Carter, Judge Robert William Hughes, Collis Potter Huntington, Henry Brainered McClellan (concerning James Breathed, Wickham's service as colonel of the 4th Virginia Cavalry Regiment, and Jeb Stuart's raid into Pennsylvania in 1862), George William Richardson, Thomas Lafayette Rosser (concerning cavalry in the Confederate State Army), David Watson Taylor, and Doctor Thomas Fanning Wood (of Wilmington, N.C., enclosing a manuscript history of the Wood, Fanning, and Coffin families).
Box 12 contains eleven volumes of Wickham's personal account books, 1875-1885, and an account book covering "household expenses at Hickory Hill." Loose accounts are scattered, but cover 1861, 1868-1888, and are heaviest in the years 1873-1879. Many of these accounts relate to farming, shipping of goods, construction of the mansion at "Hickory Hill," and furnishing the house.
The "Hickory Hill" farm materials begin with 15 volumes of "farm books," 1866-1888, which bear records of expenditures and receipts, as well as accounts with individual laborers, managers, and timbermen. Loose materials, 1871-1888, include 2 folders of records concerning the purchase of adjacent lands added to the "Hickory Hill" tract; a lease to "Knapp's" in Hanover County for conducting an egg and poultry business; an agreement concerning the care of sheep; materials concerning the construction of a stable and barn; insurance policies; a written plan for farm operations; measurements for carpeting several rooms in the mansion house; notes on the division of fields for crop rotation; notes and accounts concerning farm laborers; and miscellany.
Box 16 is wholly devoted to materials, 1867-1887, concerning "North Wales," a plantation across the Pamunkey river in Caroline County that Williams Carter Wickham managed for his cousin, Doctor Charles Carter of Philadelphia. Initial materials include a deed of William Carter, William Fanning Wickham and Williams Carter Wickham (all as executors and trustees of the estate of Williams Carter [d. 1864]) to Charles Carter; a lease to John H. Allen, an agreement concerning a debt owed by Allen's estate, and a letter of Mrs. N. V. Allen to William Fanning Wickham; a letter of E. and S. Wortham of Richmond to doctor Carter; an agreement of Williams Carter Wickham with John C. Allen as overseer; an appraisal of livestock; a map of 1878; and a lease to Williams Carter Wickham in 1882. Farm books (3 volumes) cover the period 1878-1886, while loose accounts date from the years 1877-1879. Miscellaneous items include shipping records (corn); notes on plantation operations and field divisions for crop rotation; and inventories of stock and equipment.
The next box (17) of Wickham's papers concerns the estate of Margaret William Tryon (Fanning) Cumberland of Enham Lodge, Leamington, Eng., a sister of Wickham's grandmother Mary Smith (Fanning) Wickham. These materials, 1880-1888, concern Mrs. Cumberland's bequest of personal items to Wickham. Documents that survive include correspondence of Wickham with Mrs. Cumberland, Ann Carter (Wickham) Renshaw Byerly, and London attorney William Ford, executor of Mrs. Cumberland's estate. A folder contains notes on the Fanning family; a copy of an autobiographical "statement" of Edmund Fanning; and biographical notes made by Maria Fanning. Another folder contains a sketch of a window of Lillington Church, Warwickshire, Eng., memorializing Lt. Col. Bentinck Harry Cumberland; materials concerning Fanning Grammar School, Malpeque, Prince Edward Island, Canada; notes on silver plate and jewelry; and a memorandum of assets of the estate.
Wickham followed his father as a trustee for Frances (Wickham) Graham, who came to live at "Hickory Hill." Acting with Maclurg Wickham over the years 1880-1888, Wickham maintained a few items of correspondence, accounts (including contributions to the salary of Sewall Stavely Hepbron as a rector of St. Paul's Episcopal Church in Hanover County), and records of financial advances to John Wickham (1825- 1902) and Littleton Waller Tazewell Wickham.
Williams Carter Wickham also served as a trustee under a marriage agreement between George Harrison Byrd of Baltimore and Lucy Carter Wickham, one of Wickham's nieces. The records of this trusteeship, 1857- 1892, include correspondence with Byrd, accounts, and a release issued to the estate of Williams Carter Wickham. Materials, 1876-1889, cover Wickham's activities as trustee for Reverend Edmund Wilcox Hubard and his wife Julia Leiper Taylor (a sister of Wickham's wife, Lucy). These consist of correspondence with the Hubards (of Bedford an Rappahannock counties, Va.), Henry Taylor, and William Penn Taylor; accounts and receipts; a memoranda concerning title to land in Richmond, Va.; orders of the Westmoreland County Court; and letters to Henry Taylor Wickham as executor of Williams Carter Wickham.
There follow materials concerning Wickham's years of service with the C. and O. Railway, 1872-1888. Items concerning the Central Land Company of West Virginia include an agreement of John and Daniel Kerr Stewart regarding lands in Virginia, West Virginia, and Ohio purchased by Collis Potter Huntington and his associates under contract with the C. and O.; a letter of Daniel Kerr Stewart; and accounts. Some records cover Wickham's post as receiver and consist largely of newspaper clippings, a letter to the committee for reorganization, and an agreement. Another agreement concerns fences along Wickham's property in Hanover County. Lastly, miscellany includes accounts and complimentary tickets from the Richmond City Railway Company.
Some loose Republican party materials, 1881-1887, include newspaper clippings concerning Virginia Senator William Mahone; an invitation issued to Wickham by the U.S. State Department; a petition from Hanover County voters encouraging Wickham to retain his seat in the Virginia Senate; and a letter of William Fanning Wickham [1860-1900] to Ann Carter (Wickham) Rensaw Byerly concerning General Wickham's political career. Miscellaneous land records, 1876-1878, consist of a deed to land in Hanover County owed by E. F. Baker; insurance policies on a lot and house on Cedar Street in Richmond, "Oakland," Hanover County, and the Episcopal parsonage of St. Paul's Parish, Hanover County, Va.
General Wickham's personal miscellany is comprised of a broadside, 1861, as a Virginia state senator for Hanover and Henrico counties concerning the Virginia Secession Convention; a certificate of election, 1863, to the Confederate States Congress (signed by George Wythe Munford); a code book, n.d., used for messages between Wickham and C. T. Dabney; a stock certificate, 1886, for 100 shares in Spring Valley Gold Mining Company of California; a contract, 1887, for enclosing the Wickham family section in Shockoe Hill Cemetery in Richmond; and a letter, 1882, of Henry Hall of the New York Tribune to John Page. Wickham's estate materials include a copy of his will probated in Hanover County; telegrams of condolence sent to Lucy Penn (Taylor ) Wickham and Henry Taylor Wickham (many from his railroad associates and fellow veterans like Collis Potter Huntington andFitzhugh Lee); a letter from Virginia L. Nelson; a biographical sketch of Wickham and memoranda of his Civil War service; resolutions of respect and tribute; and obituary notices and newspaper editorials.
Williams Carter Wickham married Lucy Penn Taylor in 1848 and they lived at "Hickory Hill." Mrs. Wickham's papers, in Series 6, include several dozen early letters, 1848-1866, she wrote to Elizabeth (Kane) Shields, daughter of Judge John Kintzing Kane of Philadelphia and sister of Arctic explorer Elisha Kent Kane and Thomas Leiper Kane (all of whom are mentioned in the letters, along with notes of William Fanning Wickham). Mrs. Wickham's correspondence, 1888-1913, is primarily with Henry Taylor and Henry Taylor Wickham, in part concerning "Hickory Hill." Her accounts sporadically cover the period 1875-1913, along with personal property tax returns, 1893-1909. Correspondence, 1902, of Henry Taylor Wickham concerns his mother's purchase of shares in the Chesapeake Land and Improvement Company of Richmond. Her collected genealogical notes concern the Hubard, Leiper, Pendleton, and Taylor families.
Two folders of Mrs. Wickham's personal papers concern the estate of her father, Henry Taylor of "Belvidera," Spotsylvania County, Va. These materials, 1853-1921, are made up of a letter of Taylor to Mrs. Wickham; copies of Taylor's will; a memorandum and notes of Henry Taylor Wickham; materials concerning Julia Leiper (Taylor Hubard v. Henry Taylor's administrator in the Westmoreland County Court (1864-1866) and Julia Leiper (Taylor) Hubard v. Henry Taylor etal. in the Westmoreland County Circuit Court. Materials regarding a trust created for the benefit of Lucy Penn (Taylor) Wickham consist of the appointment by Julia Dunlap (Leiper) Taylor and William Penn Taylor of William Fanning Wickham and Williams Carter Wickham as trustees; decrees and a report to the Westmoreland County Circuit Court in William Carter Wickham etal. v. Henry Taylor's executors etal.; a deed of trust and release of Henry Taylor to "Leeds Farm," Westmoreland County; extracts from the records of the Circuit Court for Spotsylvania County; and proceedings in Rosa V. Taylor v. Henry Taylor etal. in Spotsylvania Circuit Court.
Five folders of documents concern the estate of Lucy Penn (Taylor) Wickham, 1913-1915. These include copies of her numerous wills; a legal opinion of Hill Carter; inventories; correspondence and accounts of the executors. One folder contains records from Henry Taylor Wickham etal. v. Stuart Lee Dance, as guardian of the children of William Fanning Wickham (1860-1900) in the Hanover County Circuit Court (bill of complaint and exhibits; motions and decrees; depositions; accounts; notes; petitions for appeal to the Virginia Supreme Court of Appeals). "Hickory Hill" materials are comprised of a lease to Henry Taylor Wickham, 1892; financial records of William Fanning Wickham's (1860-1900) management of the farm; deeds of the heirs of Lucy Penn (Taylor) Wickham (Ann Carter (Wickham) Renshaw Byerly, Williams Carter Wickham Renshaw, and Williams Carter Wickham [1887-1985]); and a deed and agreement concerning sale of a portion of "Prospect Hill," adjoining "The Lane," to C. P. Cardwell, and access to a road called "The Boulevard" in Hanover County. Estate miscellany consists of materials concerning a debt of Sol L. Bloomberg, a memorandum and notes of Henry Taylor Wickham, and obituary notices.
Henry Taylor Wickham (1849-1943), eldest child of Williams Carter Wickham and Lucy Penn (Taylor) Wickham, also trained as an attorney and practiced for many years in Hanover County and Richmond. He was long- time general counsel for the Chesapeake and Ohio Railway Company. Henry Wickham's papers begin with a series of six letterbooks, 1931-1940, kept at his office in the First National Bank Building in Richmond. They cover personal business and family affairs, Democratic party politics, Wickham's lengthy career in the Virginia Senate, his law practice, and his activities as a member of the Westmoreland Club and supporter of the Richmond Community Fund. Reminiscences of the Civil War service of Williams Carter Wickham are sprinkled throughout these volumes. His papers make up Series 7.
Along with numerous family members, addressees (indexed in each letterbook by Wickham himself) include Matthew Page Andrews (beginning in vol. IV), Leon Maurice Nelson Bazile (begin vol. V), Harry Flood Byrd, William Duval Cardwell, Herbert Fitzpatrick McCall Frazier, Carter Glass, Newton Lewis Hall (as farm manger of "Hickory Hill"), George P. Lyon, Andrew Jackson Montague, Rosewell Page, George C. Peery, John Garland Pollard, Absalom Willis Robertson, William H. Shelton, Cornelius T. Smith, Claude Augustus Swanson, and William Munford Tuck (beginning vol. V), and the Richmond real estate management firms of Elam and Funsten, Charles A. Rose Co., and Morton G. Thalhimer, Inc.
Henry Taylor Wickham's loose correspondence, 1874-1941, is largely personal, directed mostly to family members, although some items concern his business affairs. A good number are letters of condolence on the death of Williams Carter Wickham (1820-1888). Among the more frequent or significant correspondents are Alice (Carter) Bransford (of "Shirley," Charles City County, Va.), Ann Carter (Wickham) Renshaw Byerly, William Anderson Glasgow (enclosing a typescript copy of a memoir by Frederick Johnston and letters, 1814-1815, of John Randolph of Roanoke and Custis Lee, Mildred Childe Lee, Robert Henry Renshaw, George Barksdale Wickham (while attending Virginia Military Institute,, Lexington), Williams Carter Wickham (1887-1985), and Eleanor Landis (Porcher) Windle (enclosing a typescript copy of a letter of Anne Butler (Carter) Wickham concerning the capture of William Henry Fitzhugh Lee at "Hickory Hill" by Union forces in 1863).
An account book, 1867-1870, of Henry Taylor Wickham covers his student days at Washington College (now Washington and Lee University) in Lexington and at the University of Virginia, and includes lists of law books and lines of verse written by Wickham. Along with an account book, 1942, two passbooks, 1915-1926, and a check stub book, 1922-1926, financial records also include loose accounts, 1920-1939 (mostly consisting of canceled checks before 1931).
Box 26 contains materials relating to several real estate properties managed for Wickham in the 1930s by Elam and Funsten and by Charles A. Rose Co. (1309 East Cary Street, 13 North Governor Street, and 1333 West Broad Street).
"Hickory Hill" materials fill more than three boxes (17-30). Beginning with four volumes of farm books, 1893-1913, that record wages paid to laborers, general farm accounts, and records of agricultural operations, these materials likewise include loose farm records and accounts, 1929-1943, consisting in part of time sheets, payrolls and produce statements. A few additional loose items cover agricultural operations in 1894-1898; records collected by Wickham of the southern boundary of "Hickory Hill," "South Wales," the "Lane Island" (formed from a portion of "The Lane" by the changing course of the Pamunkey river), and land belonging to the estate of Christopher Wingfield, consisting primarily of plats, surveys correspondence, and notes (most dated between 1908-1915); and contracts, 1927-1942, with Newton Lewis Hall as farm manager.
Some loose items concerning Wickham's college days include certificates and diplomas, 1867-1868, issued by Washington College (all signed by Robert E. Lee and various faculty members); a membership certificate in the alumni association signed by John Echols, Samuel H. Letcher, and others); a diploma issued by the University of Virginia, 1870, as Bachelor of Law (signed by Socrates Maupin, John Barbee Minor, and others); and an honorary doctor of laws degree conferred by Washington and Lee University, 1935.
Records concerning Wickham's lengthy career in the Virginia Senate range widely. They include vote totals in Hanover and Caroline counties for elections held in 1899 and 1907; certificates of election, 1923- 1939; a transcript of a newspaper clipping, 1906, concerning Thomas Staples Martin; clippings concerning members of the Bryan family, the Richmond Times-Dispatch, and alleged legislative corruption, 1913; certificates concerning election expenditures, 1935; materials concerning the primary and general elections of 1939; materials, 1934, concerning a proposal to alter Hanover County's form of government to a "county executive" system (newspaper clippings, notes and a letter of Dr. Early Lee Fox of Randolph-Macon College, Ashland); and a joint resolution, 1942, of the Virginia General Assembly concerning Henry Taylor Wickham.
Many of Mr. Wickham's speeches over the year survive in his personal papers. Some loose items, 1935-1942, primarily concern Democratic party politics and historical subjects in Virginia (such as Patrick Henry's political career and college life at Washington and Lee University under Robert E. Lee). Many more items are bound together in three volumes of speeches and addresses (Box 31), including a number of items written by or about Williams Carter Wickham (1820-1888). For examply, in Volume I (1860-1926) there are remarks made by Williams Carter Wickham at a meeting of citizens at Henrico courthouse, 3 December 1860, concerning instructions from electors on his course in the Virginia Senate (no. 1); an address of Williams Carter Wickham, ca. 1860, concerning a call to the U.S. Congress for a convention to amend the U.S. Constitution (no. 2); a speech of Andrew Jackson Montague, 1926, concerning Williams Carter Wickham (no. 16); numerous addresses of Henry Taylor Wickham to literary societies, veterans' groups, and local celebrations and commemorations (such as the unveiling of portraits at Hanover Court House in 1926, with biographical sketches of Henry Rose Carter, George Pitman Haw, John Enoch Mason, John Robert Taylor, and others). The remaining two volumes include the following: Volume II (1901-1937): addresses of Henry Taylor Wickham to the League of Women Voters and local woman's clubs, and as president of the Patrick Henry Centennial Association; an 1858 manuscript roll of the Hanover Dragoons (later Company G of the 4th Virginia Cavalry Regiment, C.S.A., commanded by Williams Carter Wickham); and biographical sketches of James Churchill Cooke, William Brockenbrough Newton, Samuel Cornelius Redd, and Thomas White Sydnor; and Volume III (1888-1938): primarily political campaign speeches of Henry Taylor Wickham; recollections of Robert E. Lee; and addresses to local Confederate veterans' associations.
Boxes 32 through 37 contain 12 volumes of scrapbooks assembled and indexed by Henry Taylor Wickham, 1867-1943. Each is listed separately below, with a brief reference to general and/or outstanding contents:
Scrapbook I (1867-1932): mostly newspaper clippings concerning Republican party politics; orations and speeches of Henry Taylor Wickham; Funders-Readjusters in Virginia; John Sergeant Wise (pp. 6-10); Williams Carter Wickham (pp. 12-30, 40-76); obituary notice of Williams Carter Wickham (p. 39); and broadsides, 1867-1886, of Williams Carter Wickham issued to voters of Hanover and Henrico counties (pp. 17, 70, 72).
Scrapbook II (1888-1936): largely concerns the death of Williams Carter Wickham and the monument erected in Monroe Park, by Edmund Virginius Valentine; Hanover Troop Association reunions.
Scrapbook III (1888-1905): election campaigns and service of Henry Taylor Wickham in the Virginia Senate, especially as chairman of the senate finance committee and president pro tem; broadside to voters (pp. 5- 6); Democratic party politics; the Virginia Debt Commission (concerning West Virginia's portion of the Virginia state debt).
Scrapbook IV (1905-1923): Henry Taylor Wickham's Virginia senate career and elections; letter of Thomas Staples Martin to Wickham, 1906 (p. 5); newspaper clippings and magazine articles concerning historical subjects and railroad business.
Scrapbook V (1923-1930): Virginia Senate career; historical celebrations in Hanover County; obituary notices of Admiral James Harrison Oliver of "Shirley," Charles City County, Va. (pp. 75-77); letter of Harry Flood Byrd to Wickham, 1929 (p. 92).
Scrapbook VI (1930-1934): Wickham's memoir of Judge Edmund Waddill (pp. 39-41); reports and speech of Wickham concerning the bust of Patrick Henry placed in the hall of the Virginia House of Delegates, 1932 (pp. 52ff); letter of Douglas Southall Freeman to Wickham, 1934 (p. 90).
Scrapbook VII (1934-1937): local legislative issues; letters of Francis Pendleton Gaines of Washington and Lee University (pp. 12, 24), and William Thomas Reed (pp. 20-21, concerning "Rocky Mills," Hanover County); two letters of Harry Flood Byrd (p. 94); activities as president of the Patrick Henry Bicentennial Association; texts of some speeches included.
Scrapbook VIII (1883-1937): Henry Taylor Wickham's career and speeches; broadside of Williams Carter Wickham, 1883; many clippings about Virginia Chesterman Wickham, Richmond socialite.
Scrapbook IX (1937-1938): Virginia Senate service and Democratic politics.
Scrapbook X (1939-1940): Virginia Senate career; some speeches; correspondence tipped in: R. Walton Moore (15 September 1939), Robert Kincaid Brock (1 June 1939), Harry Flood Byrd (28 February 1940), Carter Class (March 1940).
Scrapbook XI (1940-1942): Virginia Senate career.
Scrapbook XII (1942-1943): letter of Harry Floor Byrd (30 November 1942); death of Henry Taylor Wickham in March 1943.
Records from the law practice of Henry Taylor Wickham date mostly from the later years of his career. These include materials concerning Wickham's association with the C. and O. Railway Company, 1889-1935; license applications and fees, 1931-1933; updated law notes; records from Henrico County Board of Supervisors v. J. B. Bourne etal., 1934, in the Virginia Supreme Court of Appeals; and a certificate of incorporation (typescript copy), 1919, of the Richmond Gas and Electric Appliance Company (including George Barksdale Wickham as an officer).
Wickham's land and tax records consist of a deed (typescript), 1890, to lot 590 on Grace Street in Richmond; a deed (unexecuted), 1916, to land in Hanover County; personal property tax forms, 1899-1909; a title insurance policy, 1938, covering the Boulevard Apartments, 225 North Boulevard, in Richmond; and a petition (typescript copy), ca. 1920 in Henry Taylor Wickham v. Commonwealth of Virginia in the Hanover County Circuit Court (concerning personal property and income taxes).
Wickham saved a large number of newspaper clippings that cover his legal and political career, Confederate military history, and local history in Caroline and Hanover counties and the City of Richmond. He also collected notes and records on the following families: Barksdale, Carter, Fanning, Leiper, Penn, Taylor, and Wickham. His general miscellany, finally, includes cards, notes, telegrams, etc., concerning the Wickhams' 50th wedding anniversary in 1935; a power of attorney, 1938, concerning the Social security Act; newspaper clippings and an eulogy by Wickham at the funeral of Rosewell Page; historical notes on the Blair family of Virginia; notes concerning visitors to the While Sulphur Springs, W.Va., in 1875 (identified in an accompanying photograph); a letter (copy), 1926, of Judge Jake Fisher of Braxton County, W.Va., to Herbert Fitzpatrick concerning a Michael Miley photograph of Robert E. Lee; lists of books; and miscellaneous notes and lines of verse.
Wickham's estate records fill seven folders in Boxes 38-39/ They begin with obituary notices, resolutions, and memorial tributes, and certificates of death and probate. Much of the correspondence of the estate, handled by the widow, Elise Warwick (Barksdale) Wickham, and Richmond attorney R. Grayson Dashiell, is directed to Williams Carter Wickham (1887-1985). Financial records include loose accounts, 1943-1944, an account book and account statements rom the Savings Bank and Trust Company in Richmond, and a check stub book. Tax forms and receipts for the years 1940-1944 follow.